<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rab Fulton</title>
    <atom:link href="http://127.0.0.1:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://127.0.0.1:4000/</link>
    <description>Blog on Flute , bentwood ring and instrument making</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 06:04:31 +0100</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>John Conways Game of Life</title>
        <link>http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/08/02/Game-of-Life.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/08/02/Game-of-Life.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life&quot;&gt;game of Life&lt;/a&gt; is a cellular automaton. It was developed or discovered by the mathematician John Conway in 1970. The premise is that you have a grid where each cell of the grid can be coloured (alive) on blank (dead). The decision of whether a cell is alive or dead is governed by four simple rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each cell in a grid we consider it and its eight surrounding neighbors according to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Current state&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Next State&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alive with less than 2 neighbors alive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dead&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alive with 2 or 3 neighbors alive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alive&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alive with more than 3 neighbors alive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dead&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dead with 3 neighbors alive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alive&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying these rules at fixed time steps with differing starting conditions can produce remarkably complex behavior and has been show to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_completeness&quot;&gt;Turing complete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly when Mr Conway conceived this he did not run the simulation on a computer (in 1970 they could be hard to come by), but instead ran the simulation in his office using all manner of items to represent cells and marveled as patterns formed and expanded and even spread out into the hallway. Nowadays any computer or smartphone can be used to explore the Game of Life and any other rule sets you can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An other approach is a dedicated electronics device. Keen to 256 solder LED’s I made a nice life simulation that is equally at home on your desk or wall…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/life.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Game of Life&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/nP6oNeEQ0yw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one off production will be available for purchase on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;Etsy&lt;/a&gt;.
You can see some of my other creations on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/108624488609783583375/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; and for sale on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;Etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wooden Rings - Inlay</title>
        <link>http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/07/21/Wooden-Rings-Inlay.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/07/21/Wooden-Rings-Inlay.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Decided to share the process of adding a crushed stone inlay to a wooden ring. Starting with an Indian Rosewood blank I prepared earlier, a channel has to be cut to receive the inlay.
A tool called a purfling cutter (easy to make or can be purchased from a Luthier supplier) is used to score two lines on the ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-inlay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area between the scored lines can then be chiseled out. Here I am using my trusty 2mm chisel. It may be necessary to periodically re-score and chisel to reach the target depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-inlay2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-inlay3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of inlaying the stones requires a surgeons hands and a good deal of patience. Using tweezers I position half a dozen or so stones at a time in the channel. In this case I am using Turquoise and Jasper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-inlay4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A drop of thin cyanoacrylate glue is added to fix then in place. The glue has to be dropped onto the stones to avoid disturbing their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-inlay5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all the stones are set add more glue to fill any gaps before tediously filing and sanding up to 12000 grit and burnishing to a high gloss finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ring-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inlay stage 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of my rings on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/108624488609783583375/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; and for sale on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;Etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bamboo Flute Making - Part 2 - Nest</title>
        <link>http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/06/30/Flute-Making-Part-2--Nest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/06/30/Flute-Making-Part-2--Nest.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the North American flute the area where where air is directed over the splitting edge to set up the resonance to produce sound is called the birds nest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most important part of a flute and very subtle changes in its dimensions can produce wildly different results. The image below should give you an idea of the principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dimensions used for the channel (width, height and profile), the sizes of the openings, the angle and position of the cutting edge in the air stream are all critical and vary according to flute being made and its desired characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/tsh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will give some rules of thumb as guidelines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Parameter&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Ballpark value&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Splitting edge angle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30 - 45 deg&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Channel height&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1/2 mm - 1 mm&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Channel length&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20 - 30mm&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TSH width&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Up to 1/2 bore diameter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TSH length&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 * airstream channel height&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are purely suggestions and you are encouraged to experiment produce many fire sticks on your own. Bamboo is ideal for this as it is cheap to buy and already has a bore, greatly reducing the costs in time and money while you get a feel for how each parameter affects the instruments sound. Be sure to start small and slowly increase values as you voice an instrument, its easier to cut bits off than to stick them back on. There is also some fairly involved mathematics that that can be used to calculate the values if you are that way inclined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For discussion, debate and further ideas I refer you to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/nativeflutewoodworking/info&quot;&gt;NAFlute forums&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begin by taking my bamboo and making two saw cuts either side of a node. These cuts are only a few millimeters deep, you don’t want to cut through the wall!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then use a chisel to flatten the area between the two cuts. It is vital that this area is worked util completely flat and is wide enough for your desired channel and splitting edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to make this area just long enough that I can use a small engineers square to check the flatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next the geometry of the nest is marked first in pencil and then with a knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start by cutting out the channel now to a shallow depth using a chisel. Final shaping and finishing for this and other components should be left until you are voicing the instrument, but try to get a smooth and consistent depth for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next drill some holes where the air will enter the channel and for the true sound hole (TSH). Use a small knife and files to enlarge the holes and make undercuts for the splitting edge and where the airstream enters the channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally mark, score, and chisel the top half of the airstreams channel into the base of the bird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/nest6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nest stage 7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of my bamboo flutes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/108624488609783583375/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; and for sale on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bamboo Flute Making - Part 1 - Binding</title>
        <link>http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/06/27/Flute-Making-Part-1--Bindings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://127.0.0.1:4000/2015/06/27/Flute-Making-Part-1--Bindings.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I cover how to tie a binding knot commonly used by flute makers around the world to decorate, reinforce or repair an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use fishing line for my bindings, you can use any type of string or material of choice, as long as it is strong. For a binding to be effective it must be as tight as possible. Begin by taking a few meters of your line and tying one end to something solid. At the other end create a loop and pin it in place on the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next comes the trickiest part. Begin by making a few wraps round working from the pinched base of the loop upwards. Try to get as much tension as practicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now continue wrapping round by rotating the flute while pulling away from the tied end. You can walk your thumbs over the bindings as you do this to prevent the binding from slipping. As you add more wraps you can keep increasing the tension by keeping a constant pull on the line as you wrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the desired number of wraps, pin them tightly in place with your thumb and cut the line free from where you tied it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now take the free end and pass it through the top of the loop. Your loops should be much tighter than those pictured as you not simultaneously trying to operate a camera one handed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begin pulling the loose end that was used to form the initial loop until the the loop starts to pull the newly cut end under the wraps. Now hold both ends tightly and pull them until the loop is centered under the wraps. As the loop slips under you will see the cross of the line as a lump under the wraps. This allows you to gauge the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should require considerable force for this last step if wrapped the flute tightly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete the knot by trimming the ends with a scalpel and if you like add a drop of thin CA glue over the cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of my bamboo flutes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/108624488609783583375/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; and for sale on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
