<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rab Fulton</title>
    <atom:link href="http://rabfulton.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://rabfulton.github.io/</link>
    <description>Blog on Flute , bentwood ring and instrument making</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 07:52:35 +0100</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bamboo Flute Making - Part 1 - Binding</title>
        <link>http://rabfulton.github.io/2015/06/27/Flute-Making-Part-1--Bindings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rabfulton.github.io/2015/06/27/Flute-Making-Part-1--Bindings.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I cover how to tie a binding knot commonly used by flute makers around the world to decorate, reinforce or repair an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use fishing line for my bindings, you can use any type of string or material of choice, as long as it is strong. For a binding to be effective it must be as tight as possible. Begin by taking a few meters of your line and tying one end to something solid. At the other end create a loop and pin it in place on the instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next comes the trickiest part. Begin by making a few wraps round working from the pinched base of the loop upwards. Try to get as much tension as practicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now continue wrapping round by rotating the flute while pulling away from the tied end. You can walk your thumbs over the bindings as you do this to prevent the binding from slipping. As you add more wraps you can keep increasing the tension by keeping a constant pull on the line as you wrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the desired number of wraps, pin them tightly in place with your thumb and cut the line free from where you tied it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now take the free end and pass it through the top of the loop. Your loops should be much tighter than those pictured as you not simultaneously trying to operate a camera one handed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Begin pulling the loose end that was used to form the initial loop until the the loop starts to pull the newly cut end under the wraps. Now hold both ends tightly and pull them until the loop is centered under the wraps. As the loop slips under you will see the cross of the line as a lump under the wraps. This allows you to gauge the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should require considerable force for this last step if wrapped the flute tightly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete the knot by trimming the ends with a scalpel and if you like add a drop of thin CA glue over the cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bind6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Binding stage 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of my bamboo flutes on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/108624488609783583375/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; and for sale on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Soundcraft?ref=hdr_shop_menu&quot;&gt;etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
